<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More nevves from the Palatinate; and more comfort to euery true Christian, that either fauoureth the cause of religion, or wisheth well to the King of Bohemia's proceedings. / According to faithfull and honest letters, sent ouer since the beginning of March, and now published for the satisfaction of euery true English heart..</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.38</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.114.d.5[15]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99893070</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99893070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">193601</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14982)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 193601)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C27:1[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>More nevves from the Palatinate; and more comfort to euery true Christian, that either fauoureth the cause of religion, or wisheth well to the King of Bohemia's proceedings. / According to faithfull and honest letters, sent ouer since the beginning of March, and now published for the satisfaction of euery true English heart..</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXII. [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1848 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Palatinate (Germany) --  History --  Frederick V, 1610-1623 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:193601:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:193601:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MORE NEVVES From the <hi>PALATINATE; AND</hi> MORE COMFORT To euery true Chriſtian, that <hi>either fauoureth the cauſe of</hi> Religion, or wiſheth well to the KING of BOHEMIA'S proceedings.</p>
            <p>According to faithfull and honeſt Letters, <hi>ſent ouer ſince the beginning of March, and</hi> now publiſhed for the ſatisfaction of euery true Engliſh heart.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>A Ioue ſurgit op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>MDCXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:193601:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:193601:2"/>
            <head>More Newes from the <hi>Palatinate, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe hiſtory of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> captiuitie is ſo remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that it affordeth many obſeruations to the <hi>Church</hi> of God, and is like the Balme of <hi>Gilead</hi> vnto feſtring wounds, or curing ſalues vnto ſore eies: For for the times of their <hi>humiliation</hi> they were deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of all nations, their credit lay like water ſpilt out of a bowle neuer to bee gathered vp againe; the Heathen had no word for their Temple, but downe with it, downe with it, nor for the wals of the City, but let them be puld to rubbiſh, the crowne of the Prieſthood was tumbled into the durt, and <hi>Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> with the <hi>Princes</hi> were mocked to ſcorne, when they attempted to reedifie <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and to recouer their reputation. And hath it not fared thus with <hi>Count Palatine,</hi> whoſe inueſture with his euer memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and heroike <hi>Queene</hi> was for the time glorious, and the manner acceptable, till the ſupportation of his greatnes fell from him, and <hi>Prague</hi> it ſelfe ſtoode tottering in her firmneſſe, prouing like an <hi>Egyptian</hi> reede not to be truſted vnto, yea the <hi>Princes</hi> of the Vnion were exanimated, and gaue way vnto the vnreſiſtable power (as it ſeemed) of the aduerſarie: then was nothing heard of but the loſſe of his crown and dignitie, the ſurpriſing of his Countrey and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, the purſuit of his enemies, the clamors of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the deriſion of the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the exclamation of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the attempts of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:193601:3"/>and <hi>Bauaria,</hi> with all the formidable preparation, that the <hi>Emperour</hi> and houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> could make againſt him.</p>
            <p>But now comes the comfort and cure, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is reedified, the people reſtored, the Temple erected, the wall builded, the <hi>Princes</hi> ſent home againe, the Law read, the Sacrifice exalted, the Prieſthood mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, and a worke is done of admiration: for the God of breath and ſpirits blew gentle calmes vpon the violent heate of their perſecutions, and ſlacked the burnings of their outragious fires: and why may it not be thus with the <hi>Palatinate?</hi> or, if you will, the King of <hi>Bohemias</hi> proceedings? he hath hitherto had <hi>Nemeſis in tergo,</hi> and according to the prouerbe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place hath beene a <hi>Seians</hi> horſe vnto him, for in hope of reſtitution, and a peaceable ende, hee hath found no reſt, but one waue of turbulency following another: <hi>Spinola</hi> and his armie enters on the Weſt: <hi>Bavaria</hi> and his forces comes vpon the Eaſt, and the whole Countrey is trampled vpon with the cruell feete of his enemies: but now <hi>Rota fortunae in gyro,</hi> and through Gods mercy the vaile of deſpaire is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and a new face of chearefulnes appeares. For the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germany</hi> are aſhamed of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer retraction, and ſome <hi>Catholick Biſhops</hi> begin to ſuſpect a further incrochment and tyranny, and ſo promiſh faire to ſet vpright the floriſhing liberty of their Cities, which can not be done, except the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> be reſtored, the warres ended, and ſtrangers kept from vſurping the plenty of their Country.</p>
            <p>As for the Biſhop of <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> brother to the Emperour, Count <hi>Manſfeild</hi> hath alreadie abated his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:193601:3"/>ſtrength, and in a maner diſmounted him from ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding away with the triumph of preuailing, yea, he hath affrighted <hi>Leopaldus</hi> himſelfe, and thruſt vp all his enemies into Townes of Garriſons, ſo that what with the malignity of the time of the yeare, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the feare of his Greatneſſe, being 30000. ſtrong: here is nothing talkt of, but Treatiſes of pacificationwith him, and martages for attonement. For the Biſhop of <hi>Spires</hi> Country is wholy in his power, except one Fort, and euery place he comes to either compoundeth for his friendſhip, or aſſociates her ſelfe vnto him: yea, he is growne ſo ſtrong, and ſo well appointed, that there are meſſages (I dare not name them Embaſſes) ſent vnto him on all ſides, namely, from <hi>France, Venice, Hage, Loraine,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture <hi>England</hi> her ſelfe, and that worthily too. For if euer <hi>Hanniball</hi> was commended for Diſcipline, and good order in his confuſed Army, conſiſting of ſo many ſeuerall Nations, this man hath augmented his reputation for his Martiall gouernment one way, and his noble Spirit, commixed with manſuetude, and commiſeration another way: ſo that his very enemies can lay no imputation vpon him, more then amazement, what courſe this braue built Barke will take in this turbulent Ocean of defiances, when all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> ſtand thus watching one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers proceedings. And thus much for Count <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild,</hi> and the King of <hi>Bohemias</hi> hopes to ſee once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the ſcattered limbs of <hi>Pelops</hi> gathered together and the broken bones of his Fortune well ſet againe, made ſtrong and ſtronger, like broken bones indeed, that proue the better for their firſt fraction, being well cured by a cunning Surgeon.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:193601:4"/>
            <p>The elder Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> as it ſhould ſeeme, is not dead: For by reaſon of the Biſhop of <hi>Hauerſtaffs</hi> letters, the yonger Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> hath played the Souldier all this Winter, and taken in 8. or 9. Townes of the Biſhops of <hi>Ments</hi> and <hi>Cullen,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſince February Count <hi>Harry Vanderbergh</hi> is gone vp againſt him, ſince he tooke <hi>Gulick,</hi> and a <hi>Colonell</hi> of <hi>Bauaries,</hi> and another of <hi>Don Gonzales,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all 12000. foot, and 2000. Horſe, are likewiſe marched to intercept his forwardneſſe: yet hath he proued very fortunate in his expeditions, and kept his ground in deſpight of the proudeſt wraſtlers. But we ſay here, that theſe two laſt Colonells named, are retired backe againe, as taking their firſt iourney vpon a rumor, that there were 8000. Engliſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into the Countrey, and hoping of good paſſage by the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> meanes, whom theſe <hi>Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> meant to intercept. But this rumor ran her ſelfe quickly out of breath. For by the firſt of March, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of credit came, that not a Drumm was beaten in <hi>England</hi> to ſuch a purpoſe, whereupon they returned backe againe to their Generalls, for feare of Count <hi>Manſfeilds</hi> comming vpon them, and ſurprizing them vnawarres.</p>
            <p>Whilſt Count <hi>Manſfeild</hi> thus proceeded, and had his affaires carried in a ſweet paſſage boat of ſucceſſe, the Proteſtant Princes loath to be behind hand with him in correſpondency, ſeeing the great ayds which came in, and the many Forces promiſed, engag'd themſelues likewiſe to his aſſiſtance, namely, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Baben,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Wittenbergh,</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Aenſburch,</hi> and the <hi>Lanſsgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſs,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:193601:4"/>who euery one prepared 10000. men for the Spring, and made tender of their ſeruice accordingly, ſo that if performances follow, &amp; this faire ſhadow of good words haue but an equall body of ſubſtance, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleable actions, the Summer fields may be filled with an Armie of a 100000. men, which though it ſound too harſhly in the eares of Souldiers, who know, what 40000. armed men can doe, and ſeeme ridiculous to Polliticians, who preſently demand af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the money to pay them: yet is it certaine, that theſe Princes &amp; Lords of Countries haue made their tongues pronounce the iudgement, as for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the heart, and the many contingents, which may happen diſaſtrouſly, theſe are wrapped vp in the cloſet houſe of Heauen, and being <hi>arcana coeli,</hi> it is not for polluted hands to reach at them, no more then for vs to know, whether <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> will goe on, as he hath done, to hold the Emperor play in thoſe quarters, which if he doe, then let equall men iudge (for all there is a report, that there are 8000. men come out of <hi>Italy</hi> to <hi>Leopaldus</hi>) whether the Emperor can be any way ſo ſtrong, as the Princes, I might better ſay, his Excellency Count <hi>Manſfeild.</hi> For without controuerſie, he is now ſuch a ſpirit raiſd that I beleeue will hardly be coniured downe againe by ſuch forces, as the Emperor can either ſpare, or prouide ſo ſoone. But the Summer is the time that Armies goe into the fields, and ſo till that time, we will ſuſpend all predictions, and anticipations.</p>
            <p>The faſt letters from <hi>Vienna</hi> report diuers things, both of the Emperors pretended mariage, and of the Turkes making peace with <hi>Poland;</hi> but eſpecially,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:193601:5"/>concerning the contracts with the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> which hath ſpent moſt part of the Winter in their Treaties, and is indeed ſuſpected not to haue any good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, becauſe <hi>Bethelem Gabor</hi> will not conclude it without the Emperour of <hi>Turkes</hi> conſent, to whom he is Tributary; and the <hi>Turke</hi> will not conſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he pretends that the Emperor hath broken with him, and ſet vpon his friends in his abſence, or not kept promiſe in ſending his Embaſſador to the <hi>Sacraporta,</hi> as hath bin the cuſtome, and ſo to attend him in his warres. Thus inſteed of reconciliation, is he rather threatned, and for any thing we heare, the Prince of <hi>Tranſiluania</hi> affects the reſtitution of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and will proſecute his recouery as farre as he can, or is able. But which way ſoeuer it chance, <hi>Dulce Bellum inexpertis,</hi> and the warre hath not onely made ſcarres in the face of this pleaſant Countrey, but filled it with wrinckles, which haue taken in ſo much ſoile, and durt, and ſweat, that I am affrayd the running water of peace will hardly waſh it cleane againe in good time, and it will ſcarce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer her priſtinat glory in many yeares. But of all other things moſt lamentable, the Church of God hath ſuffered deuaſtation, and the backes and ſides of Religion haue beene laſhed with cruell ſtripes, and the tormentors hand hath gon ouer them and ouer them againe: For <hi>Idolatry</hi> hath made the walls of thoſe Churches weepe, where God hath beene truely worſhipped, and not the name of an Image heard in many yeares. The pulpits haue beene trampled in with thoſe obſcoene feet, whoſe maſters haue trod vp on the graues of poore deceaſed <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:193601:5"/>name of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> thought them onely worthy to be receptacles for their ordure, making their Chappels a very Stewes: the houſes which haue lodged their garriſons, haue been filled with their ſtrumpets, who haue made the hearts of the owners ſad againe, with their filthy proſtitution, abominable Maſſes, ſongs of ribaldry, inuectiues againſt Chriſt and his Goſpel, and many other fearefull impieties of ſuperſtition and blaſphemie: yea all places haue beene repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed like the groues and alrars of the heathen, with mixtures of incenſe and ſacrifice, which I know, ſtinck worſe then the ſmell of a dung-hill in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of our ſanctifier, and great God, ſo that I make no queſtion, he will one day take his owne cauſe in hand, and deliuer vs from this vſurpation and intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo that for this point I end with the Motto,
<q>Dies dabit, quod dies negat.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I will not diſpute neither of the prerogatiue of Conquerors, nor condition of the conquered, of the riches of <hi>Emperours,</hi> nor the power of <hi>Princes,</hi> of the treaſure of <hi>Kings,</hi> nor aboundant wealth of <hi>Monarchs</hi> of the neceſſitie of the Souldiers, who muſt either liue vpon their prey, ſalary, or ſpoyle, or the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences of a gariſon in a Country ouer-watched with many diſaſtrous accidents. But this I am ſure of, that thoſe ſouldiers which <hi>Spinola</hi> left behind him, are not onely waſted with many malignant circumſtances, but wearied and tormented for want of pay and entertainment: Inſomuch that <hi>Don Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſales de Cordira</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh Generall</hi> laid a new impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition vpon that part of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> vnder his iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of a 100000 dollers, which amounteth to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:193601:6"/>20000. lib. ſterling, whereabout the people were mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably handled: For although they pleaded the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſtation of their Countrey, and the many wreſtings from them the bleſſings which God had imparted af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter great toile, labour, and endurances: yet nothing ſerued the turne but preſent money, and the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines had much adoe to pacifie the Souldiers before the taxe was gathered, and the impoſition raiſed.</p>
            <p>By this time, it is the midſt of February, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is time to tell you, what a hard Winter wee haue had, and what ſtrange ſights wee haue ſeene. The <hi>Palatinate</hi> hath beene ſubiect to ſuch froſt and ſnow, that the <hi>Rhene</hi> hath beene frozen 7. or 8. weeks together, and ſince it began to thaw, which was the 5. of February, we haue had drie and cloſe weather, yet faire and ſroſty mornings: then grew it cloſe and miſty againe 2. or 3. dayes, afterwards it waxed warm but not long: then the mornings brought vs ſmall raine till ten of the clocke, but the 14. and 15. were very wet, by reaſon of which vncertainty of weather many <hi>proiects</hi> were diſappointed, and diverſe excur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions being made, the Souldiers returned without effecting their purpoſes: yet did <hi>Generall Vere</hi> ouerſlip no opportunitie, which either ſerued to annoy the enemy, or relieue his friends, hee viſited the ſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and gariſons, &amp; ſupplied their wants as he could, he made new <hi>ramparts</hi> at <hi>Hidelburg,</hi> leauing therein Sir <hi>Garret Herbert</hi> as I take it with 2. Companies of Engliſh: but the maine gouerment was vnder a <hi>dutch Colonell,</hi> he fortified <hi>Franckendale,</hi> and the ſconces on the paſſages, hee watched <hi>Mainhem</hi> and lay therein himſelfe: he reveiwed all other places, which ſtood
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:193601:6"/>in neede of his care, and dilligence, and ſo much for weather, now to our ſights and apparitions.</p>
            <p>The 5. of this preſent February, about one of the clock, there appeared very plainly 3. full coloured Raine-bowes, one bending from <hi>ſouth ſouth-eaſt</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>north:</hi> the other oppoſite to it from <hi>ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt northward,</hi> the third was called <hi>Iris Verticalis,</hi> whoſe <hi>Center</hi> was the <hi>Sunne</hi> it ſelfe: there were alſo 3. more dimmer and not ſo well coloured, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Sunne</hi> as it were, but yet of diſtance ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: The night following were many flaſhings of the aire of lightning, and as it hapneth in ſuch caſes ſome there were, that ſaw armed men fighting, and ſome that heard the clasſhings of armour, and ſome, that ſayd plainely theſe things were not cuſtomary, but portended tumultuary convulſions on all ſides: I confeſſe I remembred the Starre 1618. and made a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of many accidents, which haue hapned ſince, and although wee were not much amazed at theſe things, becauſe there was no preuenting of that which God had appointed: yet it made vs make this vſe, to pray to God to diuert his iudgment from vs, and continue his mercy towards vs, as for coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the worſt, which was warre, blood, and trouble, who could not apprehend as much, without whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of propheſies, or calculating natiuities, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting any fearefull man, when all <hi>Europe</hi> was in Armes, and the <hi>Princes</hi> of the earth ſtood gaſing at one anothers Fortunes.</p>
            <p>By this time Count <hi>Manſfeild</hi> had ſent to <hi>Loraine,</hi> and had likewiſe anſwer from the Duke, which ſome will haue to this purpoſe, That for his owne part he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:193601:7"/>was willing to giue way for his paſſage, whether he meant to goe to <hi>Artoies,</hi> or <hi>France:</hi> But the King of <hi>France</hi> would by no means conſent thereunto, which whether it were pleaſing to his Excellency or no, I will not diſpute: this I am ſure, that it made his own Souldiers talke at randome, that he meant to diuert the warre from the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and either draw it into <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Flanders.</hi> As for the hope of rendition, he would not medle with other Princes deſignes, but in a maner he warranted the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> a better recompence then the rendition of his Countrey, or peraduenture the Crowne of <hi>Bohemia</hi> it ſelfe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon reciprocall letters haue paſſed betweene them, and no doubt there ſhall no enterpriſe be ſet on foot, but by direction of a Councell of warre from the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and ſo running to one another with ſweet conueiance, Count <hi>Manſfeild</hi> ſhall be (as it were) the Ceſterne to entertaine the water comming from theſe Springs: For although the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> lieth now quiet at the <hi>Hage,</hi> yet no queſtion is his ſpirit working in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, and time will perfect that, which we now imagine is an vnperfect <hi>Chaos</hi> of confuſion, and ſo much for the buſines as it hangeth in ſuſpence, and cannot yet make euen the skoales of miſchiefe and miſfortune, as we prophanely abuſe that tearme, and <hi>Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I vnderſtand by many meſſengers, that your <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantos</hi> in <hi>England</hi> are ſo tranſlated, and obſequious to the Dutch Coppies, that they neuer mention any exployt of the Engliſh, nor vouchſafe to attribute the glory of any enterpriſe vnto them, as forgetting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:193601:7"/>Captaine <hi>Boroghs,</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Franckendale,</hi> and diuers valiant Gentilmen in other places, nay, they ſcarce mention <hi>Generall Vere</hi> himſelfe, who is worthy of all memory, for his conſtant reſolution, and noble courage in theſe wants &amp; endurances: For although ſome Polliticians haue giuen it out, that <hi>Spinola</hi> might as well haue run all ouer the Countrey, as doe that he did, yea, taken <hi>Heidelberg</hi> it ſelfe, if he had kept his Armie together, and therefore that which was left vndon, muſt be imputed to his commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or peraduenture, directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s from higher powers: yet will not I giue way to ſuch opinion, but anſwere plainly and honeſtly, that by that time the Engliſh had fortified the places, and hunted the enemy with ſet Batalions, it was not ſo eaſie to climbe trenches and ramparts, and come ouer the heads of Pikes, or ſtop the mouthes of Cannons: Witneſſe the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of <hi>Bauaria</hi> himſelfe, who ambitiouſly ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the whole <hi>Palatinate,</hi> as a gift of the Emperor, came forward a pace with proud ſteps to ſtraddle o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it like a <hi>Coloſſus,</hi> and thought at once to inueſt himſelfe with her robe and Coronet: but GOD be thanked, it is yet vndone, and if euer a Prouerbe was verified, we may well ſay by him;
<q>Multa cadunt inter Calicem, ſuprema<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> labra.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But to my firſt purpoſe, ſeeing the Dutch will tell you no Stories of the Engliſh, I will tell you one of the Dutch.</p>
            <p>Vpon the laſt of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> when the Froſt began to breake, a certaine Dutch Captaine, full of preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous words, and oſtentous braggs, reſolued to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:193601:8"/>ſome exployt vpon <hi>Steine</hi> a Caſtle, which ſtood in the midſt of woods and waters, and for which <hi>Don Gonzalis</hi> firſt brake the Truce, the 20. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt: whereupon as well acquainted with the paſſages, and all the ſecrets of the place, he vndertooke this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe with a 100. men, and came accordingly thither by foure a clocke in the morning, nor did he this temerariouſly to the outward ſhow, but had good ſearches and ſcout-maſters before to vnderſtand the ſtrength of the place (beſides his owne knowledge of the ſcituation) the number of the Guard, and the order of the Sentinells, with all other things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to a ſurpriſe. But ſee the miſfortune! as ſoone as euer the Sentinell had diſcharged his Muſket, he quickly fell from his reſolution, as a man diſtracted, and very baſely cryed out, We are diſcouered, <hi>A retreat, a retreat;</hi> and when the Souldiers anſwered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, there was yet no danger, nor could be any in the proſecution, he rode in amongſt them, and beat them backe moſt cowardly, as if 10000. enemies had come toward them: yet for all this, when he and his company had thus runne away, at the ſame time a Dutch Lieutenant, with leſſe then fiftie men, ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and cut off the whole Court of Guard in the Sconſe before the Caſtle, tooke many priſoners, and made the reſt ſecure themſelues with in the wals, from whence they played apace, but did not hurt aboue one man: but by reaſon they wanted their <hi>Patars,</hi> and that the Captaine and his company were gone ſo far off, they could not enter the gates, nor ſap the wals, but made a braue Retreat indeed, and came ſafely to their <hi>Rendezuous.</hi> But the Captaine in ſtead of ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:193601:8"/>an account to my Lord <hi>Generall</hi> of his actions, ran away for ſhame, and was no more ſeene in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique among the Souldiers; yet had the Lieutenant thankes, and a gratuitie, according to the worthines of his deſeruing.</p>
            <p>This I thought good to ſet downe as a taſt of ſuch bitter pils, we are many times co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to ſwallow, as either the <hi>Dutch</hi> proue vnruly, or out of ſuſpition of ouer-maſtring, caſt vp an vntoward account of their owne weaknes: Thus loſt we this opportunitie of the laſting froſt, conſidering the place was of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and now muſt be contented: For in open weather the Caſtle is in a manner impregnable, as ſtanding (as I ſayd) in ſuch a faſtneſſe of wood, and water.</p>
            <p>Whiles the affaires of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> cheered our hearts with the expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good deliuerance from all our troubles, newes came for certaine, that the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> was married, and the <hi>Pope</hi> had ſent the <hi>Empreſſe</hi> an hallowed roſe of gold, with other reliques, which ſhee receiued very graciouſly at the hands of <hi>Seigneur Peroſpi</hi> his <hi>Nuntio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the froſt and ſnow was very great, yet it is ſayd, that the <hi>Neopolitans,</hi> and other <hi>Italian</hi> ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers taking advantage of certaine contracts, and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles betweene the <hi>Grizons,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> garriſons, haue aduentured through the paſſages, and with the loſſe of 800. men by the aſperity of wether, preſented a body of 800. to <hi>Leopaldus,</hi> who thereupon attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both to recouer <hi>Elſas Saueren,</hi> and his Countrey, which were ſpoyled a new for breach of their faith to <hi>Count Manſfeild,</hi> and to ſend a defiance to his <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:193601:9"/>who for all the report of the <hi>Catholicke</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſmiled at the <hi>bravado,</hi> as reſoluing vpon other maner of buſines, then fighting of a battle in a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try where nothing was to be gotten.</p>
            <p>About the 15. of February, a great fire hapned at <hi>Landenburgh,</hi> as you goe to <hi>Heidelburgh,</hi> which not onely burnt down the two great gates, but conſumed many roomes and chambers, yea diuers ſouldiers, that had the watch of the Tower, and guard of the place: yet was the miſcheife imputed to the watch, and the Country much affrighted came in to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine to the Gouernour of the offenders.</p>
            <p>Report is ſtill buſie amongſt vs, and to comfort vs in our wants and diſtreſſe in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> aſſureth that all the Countries round about, namely <hi>Spires, Elſos, Straſburgh,</hi> and all the biſhopricks in generall, are ready to ſtarue, and haue not ſufficient viands for their owne inhabitants, whereupon <hi>Count Manſfield</hi> hath written to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Wittenbergh,</hi> for paſſage through his country, ſo that it is ſuppoſed, he either intendeth for <hi>Bavaria</hi> or <hi>Vienna,</hi> vnles he play the lap wing, who commonly flieth furtheſt from her neſt, &amp; ſo may he giue notice of one thing, and yet pretend another.</p>
            <p>Much about this time his Excellency <hi>Count Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> vnderſtanding that the <hi>Bavarian Regiment</hi> was vnder the command of <hi>Montaigne,</hi> and lay quartred vpon the <hi>neckar</hi> in the <hi>ampt moſbegg,</hi> ſent to the town of <hi>Hagenaw</hi> for a new compoſition, &amp; ſo had 30000. Florens by way of a taxe or new leauie: thus doth he both increaſe and inrich himſelfe, yet is not his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination knowne, what he will do with his great
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:193601:9"/>armie, more then that (as they ſay) he writ letters of comfort to <hi>Heidelburg,</hi> and <hi>Generall Vere</hi> at <hi>Mainhem,</hi> whoſe horſe went out the ſame day vpon an expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and tooke many wagons loaden with prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and diuers priſoners, who were ranſomed after the maners of ſoldiers: they went out to releiue <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgg</hi> and other townes in the enemies poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for they were ſubiect to hunger and cold, and there periſhed of the inhabitants very neere 600.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Graue Hendrick Van</hi> being with the garriſons of <hi>Gulick,</hi> had paſſed the <hi>Rhene,</hi> as was ſuppoſed, to ioyne with the <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> that were comming into <hi>Haſſia:</hi> the Duke <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> ſtored <hi>Pater borne</hi> and many townes with ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and reſolued to encounter them, which way ſo euer they came or went, but as they had done once before, ſome occaſion deuided them all, for they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer met; but for any thing I heare, they were glad of good ſhelter in this cold and vnſeaſonable weather.</p>
            <p>There are other things, of which I could write, but I am ſure you dare not publiſh: For ſuch is the nature of rumor, that a little truth begetteth many abſurdities, like a Ball of ſnow, which by often row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling groweth bigger and bigger; and therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt at this time, till better occaſion preſent better mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto me, which, I am ſure, is now in the wombe, and longeth for a birth and faire deliuerance. The ſumme of all is, that God (as he hath done) will maintaine the cauſe of his Church; and Religion (as ſhe hath done) will ſhew her owne ſplendor, in deſpight of clouds and oppoſition, like the Sunne, that may be a while obſcured, but at laſt openeth the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:193601:10"/>vapours, and commeth like a Bride out of her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. As for man, though there is no quarrell ſo iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable as the defence of the Goſpel, and propagation of the ſame, if yet there be mixtures of priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, enuie, ambition, deſire of renowne, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that which we call heroike vallour in the ampliation of territories; it will taint the good cauſe, like dead flies in boxes of ointments, and God will haue no ſuch mixtures, as collaterall corruption to be ſhadowed vnder the defence of his Truth: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I make no queſtion of a recouery in the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> becauſe I ſee apparantly ſo many good ſoules and diſpoſitions both grieued at the ceſſation of the publique Miniſtry in many places, and vexed againe at the impietie of Papiſticall <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who dare bring the pattern of the Altar of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> into the temple of God. And as for their obiection, that maintaine, that the Souldiers of Count <hi>Manſfeilds</hi> Armies, and the reſt of the Princes, which pretend the defence of the King of BOHEMIA's cauſe, are either moſt of them Papiſts, or of no Religion: and yet forrage, and ſpoyle the Countries of Catholick Biſhops, and ſuch Lords, as know no other but the obedience of the Popes Supremacy. I anſwer plainly and honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: What of that? God will bring his purpoſe this way about: Though <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> be an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, yet for the time ſhall his Idoll be trampled to duſt, and be no more worſhipped: Though <hi>Cyrus</hi> be a Heathen, yet God calleth him his ſeruant, and he ſhall ſend the people to re-edifie <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the veſſels of Gold backe againe to adorne the Temple: And though Papiſts maintaine their abſurd opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:193601:10"/>yet ſhall they be made inſtruments of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and euen deſtroy one another, till either they be conuerted, or effectuate that worke, which he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them about: In which expectation we remaine at this houre, and exhilerate our ſelues, that the buſineſſe in hand is in ſo good a forwardneſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:193601:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:193601:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
